Okay, let's now take up the famous example of the harmonic oscillator, which you will
recall even from your studies of elementary classical mechanics, is a situation in which
we have a force that's a restoring force, that's why we have the minus sign and the
strength of the force is proportional to the displacement x. So the example that you can
have in mind for this can be, for instance, a spring with a mass on it that is oscillating,
vibrating back and forth. Now, bearing in mind that the force F is related to a potential
in the usual way of minus dv/dx, we see therefore that our potential v(x) is equal to 1/2 kx^2.
Now bear in mind as well that because F=ma, we have our classical equations of motion
being md2x/dt^2 is equal to -kx, and that gives rise to classical solutions that we
can immediately write down in the form x(t)=a*sin(omega t)+b*cos(omega t), where a and b are coefficients
that are determined by the initial conditions, by the boundary conditions, and as expression
omega is defined to be the square root of the spring constant k over the mass m. Now
this example of the harmonic oscillator equation is incredibly important, and you might say
why, why does it crop up so much in physics? And if you haven't seen that yet, you will
see it, just about every problem you ever solve analytically in physics in some sense is related
to the harmonic oscillator. The reason is simply this, if you take any potential at all in
the world, and you expand it in the vicinity of its minimum, then if you call x0 that min,
then we have v(x0), because x0 is assumed to be a minimum, then next term, which is
proportional to the derivative of v with respect to x at x0, gives you 0, and therefore the
first non-trivial term is the quadratic term, 1/2k(x-x0)^2, where k in this expression just
comes from the second derivative of v with respect to x^2 evaluated at x0. So you see
right away that any potential in the world, if you are looking sufficiently near a stable
minimum, will have deviations of the potential from the value of the potential at the minimum
given by 1/2k(x^2) or 1/2kΔ(x^2), which of course is exactly the potential that we have
associated with the harmonic oscillator. And that's why this example comes up all the time.
Any potential near its minimum gives rise to fluctuations that look like a harmonic
oscillator. Now of course this is the classical description. If we go on to the quantum description,
well now we know how to do that in terms of Schrodinger's equation, which gives us there
for the equation, whoops, let me go back to where I was here, gives us our equation minus
h-bar squared over 2m d2 psi dx^2 plus v(x), which we'll write as 1/2m omega squared x^2
psi equals e psi. So there we have the quantum mechanical version of the harmonic oscillator
seeking the energy eigenstates. Now here is the thing, there are two, well there are many
ways, but let me just broadly speak, and there are two ways that you can go about solving
this Schrodinger equation for the harmonic oscillator. The first is, well look, you can
just do brute force solution of a differential equation, right? It's not that hard. However,
you can also take a far more clever approach, which is an algebraic approach, and that more
clever approach is the one that I'd like to spend a little bit of time now on developing.
And this clever approach comes initially, I believe historically this is accurate, from
Paul Dirac, one of the great pioneers of quantum mechanics, and here's how it goes. So remembering
that the momentum can be written as minus ih-bar d by dx, then the Schrodinger equation
that we wrote down can simply now be written as 1/2m. p^2 will give us that first equation,
first term of the equation, and then the potential term we'll write as m omega x^2 times psi,
and we want all of this to be equal to e*psi. That's the equation that we want to solve.
Now our inspiration for solving this, or perhaps Dirac's inspiration for solving this, will
be to note the very simple fact that we're all familiar with, that for ordinary numbers,
a^2 + b^2, that can be factored as a + ib times a - ib. Good. So let's try to play the
same game now, but with x's and p's, these operators in quantum mechanics. In other words,
we're going to try to factor the Schrodinger differential equation. So to that end, let's
consider two new operators whose definition I'll give you, and the motivation will become
clear in just a moment. Let's call them a+ or - that are defined to be 1/sqrt(2h-bar
m omega - + (that will be corresponding to the plus and minus on the a) ip + m omega
x. Okay, so this is our definition of a+ and a-, and now I want you to note the following.
Let's consider a- times a+. What does that equal? Well, that is 1/2h-bar m omega from
the coefficient out front. The a- term will give us minus, or the a- term gives us a plus,
sorry about that, ip + m omega x. And then the a+ gives us the -ip + m omega x. Good.
Okay, now let's just expand this out a little bit. So that's 1/2h-bar m omega times, well,
the ip with the -ip gives us our p squared. The m omega x times itself will give us our
m omega x squared. And then the remaining part is minus i m omega, after we do a little
bit of cancellation of the h-bar that comes into this, the i omega times xp minus px.
Let me just make sure I haven't left out any terms. H-bar m omega, yeah, no cancellation,
perfect. Alright, excellent. Okay, given that now, let me just note that if a+ and a- were
ordinary numbers, right, so for classical numbers, of course, xp minus px would simply
be equal to zero, and that's how, of course, you get to the usual identity that for numbers
I've written over here. But for operators, for quantum operators, things are a little
bit different because xp is not equal to px, so their difference, xp minus px, which we
can write as bracket x, p, this generally will not equal to zero. And let me show you
that explicitly right now. And the way to do this, the way you should always do this
when it comes to operator ordering, is to act on a function, a test function, to see
how the bracket operates. So let me show you that. So let's take our bracket xp, let's
act on psi of x, and we'll just spell this out. So that's x times minus i h-bar d by
dx, there's the p, times psi. And now it's the same thing but in reverse order, minus
i h-bar d by dx, x, psi. Alright, this now we can easily expand out as x times minus
i h-bar d psi dx. And notice that we have another term, the first one, when the dx acts
on the x itself, that will give us a term that looks just like this. Well, I actually
said that a little bit backwards, let me take that back a little bit. So let me operate
first with the dx on the psi, and pull the x out so I can get my initial cancellation
over here, x i h-bar times d psi dx. But there's a second term from the product rule of course,
where the dx now acts just on the x part over here, and that will give us a plus i h-bar
times psi of x. So we get this nice little cancellation over here between this term and
this term, but unlike with ordinary numbers with quantum operators, we have something
left over. x p operating on psi of x is equal to i h-bar psi of x. And since psi of x is
a completely general function, just a test function, maybe I should have given it a different
name, call it f or t for test function, it doesn't matter, we come to the general recognition
that x, p as an operator is equal to i h-bar. Good. Okay, so given that, let me make that
box a little bit nicer, excellent. Okay. Alright, so given that now, we can write our expression
for the product of a minus times a plus, that's equal to 1 over 2 h-bar m omega times p squared
plus m omega x squared, and now that commutator, the bracket of x and p gives us minus i m
omega, and the bracket part itself is i h-bar. Okay, so if we now look at this, it's kind
of beautiful. We have 1 over h-bar omega times something which you'll note is nothing but
our Hamiltonian h because we have our nice 1 over 2 m p squared plus our potential term
x squared, and we have an additional term left over at the end here, which is a factor
of one half coming from the bracket term on the far right-hand side. From that now, we
can solve for the Hamiltonian h is equal to h-bar omega times a minus a plus minus one
half. Beautiful, simple little formula where we have now successfully factored the quantum
mechanical Hamiltonian into the product of a minus and a plus with a little correction
term, this little correction piece which is vital, this term of minus one half. Now similarly,
I'm not going to go through the calculation because it's effectively identical. You could
also have done the same calculation multiplying not a minus times a plus but a plus times
a minus, and if you do that, it's a good exercise just to get practice. You will find h equals
h-bar omega a plus times a minus plus one half. That's the only difference when you change
the order of a plus and a minus, and from this you can immediately see, or in fact you
can just calculate it directly from the definition of a plus and a minus. You see that we have
the commutator, the bracket of a minus with a plus is equal to one. You can see that immediately
from the expressions above just by subtracting them, or you could have done that directly.
Good. All right. We're almost at the finish line here because here is the key observation
once we've done this factoring. Key observation. In fact, there are two key observations. This
is really the first of them. Imagine that we have some eigenfunction psi of energy E
of this quantum mechanical harmonic oscillator. The claim is that if you act with a plus or
a minus on this given eigenfunction and then operate with the Hamiltonian h, you will still
have an eigenfunction, but the eigenvalue will be different. It will be E either increased
or decreased by an amount h-bar omega. In fact, let me move this all over so I can fit
this nicely on the screen here. That would be E plus or minus h-bar omega times a plus
minus acting on psi. You see the beauty here is given one eigenfunction of a given eigenvalue,
these operators that are called raising and lowering operators for reasons now become
clear because a plus raises the energy by an amount h-bar omega and it is an eigenfunction
because this is proportional to a plus acting on psi and a minus lowers the energy by an
amount h-bar omega and indeed, I don't know if you can see that minus, a minus is itself
an eigenfunction as well. That's the key observation and let me just show you how to prove that.
It's quite simple. You just do this one by following your nose. Let's do h on a plus
psi. This is equal to h-bar omega. Now let me substitute in for the Hamiltonian a plus,
a minus plus one half acting on a plus psi. Now notice what we can do here. We can pull
out an a plus from here and an a plus from this term as well. Let me just do that in
one step if you don't mind. a plus h-bar omega. When you pull out this first a plus,
what will be left is a minus times a plus and by pulling out the a plus in this term,
all that will be left is one half on psi. Now that's quite nice because you will recognize
this term over here from our calculation above. This looks just like the Hamiltonian except
it's actually the Hamiltonian augmented by h-bar omega. If we go back to our expression
for h, when it's a minus a plus, it needs to be a minus sign but we have over here a
minus a plus and a plus sign and the difference between them is just a factor of one which
when multiplied by the h-bar omega out front gives us an h-bar omega inside. Of course
this is all acting on psi and that's nice because h acting on psi just gives us a factor
of e. After all psi was defined to be an eigenfunction of h with eigenvalue e. The a plus now can
pull right through those numbers. Let me just bring in the h-bar omega here as well and
so this is all multiplied by the function a plus acting on psi and now this is beautiful
because this is h acting on a plus psi is equal to a number, the eigenvalue, e plus
h-bar omega acting on the very same function. Therefore it is an eigenfunction. We have
successfully raised the energy by an amount h-bar omega. Similarly I'm not going to go
through it, same calculation, if you act with a minus on psi you will get e minus h-bar
omega, it is still an eigenfunction but now the eigenvalue has gone down by an amount
h-bar omega. And the beauty of this is given this one eigenfunction psi of eigenvalue e,
we now can from it generate a whole tower of eigenfunctions. We can act with a minus
a whole bunch of times, so let me just a minus squared on psi, a minus on psi, psi itself
or we can act with a plus on psi or a plus squared on psi and so on. So given one eigenfunction
we get a whole series or a whole tower of eigenfunctions whose eigenvalues start with
an eigenvalue e, in fact let me use a different color to make this a little bit more clear,
I'll use red. So this guy has eigenvalue energy e, this one has eigenvalue e plus h-bar, this
has e plus 2 h-bar, this has e minus h-bar omega, this has e minus 2 h-bar omega and
on it goes. So that's beautiful, we have an algorithm for generating new eigenfunctions
from old ones. Now finally I mentioned there's two key observations, let me go to the second
key observation with simply that because the energy e needs to be greater than the minimum
of the potential energy, we can't continue this series downwards indefinitely, right?
Because at some point this energy e minus n h-bar omega is going to be less than v-min
and that's not okay. So what that means is there has to be some number n such that when
we act with this lowering operator n times on our original eigenfunction it must vanish,
it cannot be non-zero otherwise we would have generated an eigenfunction whose energy
was less than the minimum of the potential energy which cannot happen. So let's write
this as a minus acting on a minus to the n minus 1 psi equals zero and let's just call
this guy psi zero, the last eigenfunction that can be achieved by using the lowering
operator because if you use the lowering operator one more time you get zero. That's a beautiful
equation too because now let's use our definition for a minus so it's 1 over square root of
2 h-bar m omega i p plus m omega x psi not equal zero or as a differential equation let's
spell it out 1 over 2 h-bar m omega times h-bar d by d x plus m omega x psi not equal
zero and that is a differential equation that we can solve very easily, just a nice Gaussian
e to the minus m omega over 2 h-bar x squared and so we have gotten our lowest energy eigenfunction
whose energy eigenvalue e not is such that you can't go any lower than that and from
psi not now since we're now sort of at the bottom of the series, the bottom of the tower,
psi not with energy eigenvalue e not goes to a plus on psi not which is e not plus h-bar
omega a plus acting twice takes us to e not plus 2 h-bar omega and on and on it goes to
generate the rest of the eigenfunctions, the rest of the eigenvalues.
[BLANK_AUDIO]